Finding Aid for Chase S. Osborn Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Political Papers, 1900-1940
  - Senatorial campaign, 1930
    - Correspondence of county campaigners and biographical sketches
      - Alcona--Kent (Box 113)
      - Lake--Wayne (Box 113)
    - Correspondence in state, June 30-September 1930 (Box 113)
    - Correspondence out of state, July 3-September 10, 1930 (Box 113)
    - Correspondence campaign materials and related correspondence (Box 113)
    - Speeches, August 22-September 6, 1930 (Box 113)
    - Press statements (Box 113)
    - Subject files, James Couzens (Box 113)
    - Subject files, Workmen's Compensation (Box 113)
    - Newsclippings, 4 folders (Box 113)
    - Miscellanea (radio schedule, lists of people, and correspondence) (Box 114)
  - Presidential Campaign miscellanea, 1932 (Box 114)
  - Papers of the Fitzgerald for Governor Campaign, 1934 (Box 114)
  - Gubernatorial Election of, 1940
    - Correspondence, February 6-May 22, 1940 (Box 114)
    - Correspondence, May 23-June 8, 1940 (Box 114)
    - Newspaper clippings, 7 folders (Box 114)
  - Wendell Willkie presidential campaign (Osborn editorials), 1940 (Box 114)
  - Miscellaneous political materials, 2 folders (Box 114)
- Mining, Timber, and Land Investments, 1883-1940
  Mining, Timber, and Land Investments (1883-1940; 7.4 linear feet) documents Osborn's many business and financial dealings. Of special note are those files pertaining to his iron mining business resulting from his discovery of iron near Sudbury in Ontario. There is also considerable material resulting from his involvement with the Michigan Iron and Land Company and pertaining to his numerous investments in Michigan timber lands. Portions of this series are unprocessed.
  - Moose Mountain Ltd., (Ontario, Canada)
    - Correspondence, 1901-1926; 2 folders (Box 114)
    - Contracts and charters (Box 114)
    - Financial (Box 114)
    - Mineral evaluations and estimations (Box 114)
    - Minutes, 1903-1905 (Box 114)
    - David A. Aitken vs. Chase S. Osborn, case concerning Moose Mountain rights (Box 114)
  - Hutton Mining Company
    - Correspondence, 1902-1905 (Box 114)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1902-1905 (Box 114)
  - Hutton-Moose Mountain Mining Co.-Joint Projects
    - Financial statements, 1904-1905 (Box 114)
    - Maps (Box 114)
    - Legal papers, 1903-1905 (Box 114)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1902-1905 (Box 114)
  - A-Z, 1902 (Box 114)
    (Sudbury mining investments)
  - Miscellaneous mining reports (Box 114)
  - Miscellaneous geological maps (Box 114)
  - Mining A-Z, 1902; 4 folders (Box 114)
  - A-Z (Moose Mountain), 1903-1904; 3 folders (Box 115)
  - A-Z (Moose Mountain), 1905 (Box 115)
  - Michigan Iron and Land Company
    - Correspondence, August 1919-1928; 41 folders (Box 115)
    - Dividend allotments, 1920 (Box 115)
    - Report of audit, 1920 (Box 115)
    - Legal papers, 1918-1920 (Box 115)
  - Michigan Iron and Land Company
    - Newsclippings, 1919-1921 (Box 116)
    - Maps, 2 folders (Box 116)
    - Annual reports, 1903-1908; 1919 (Box 116)
    - Financial records, 1913-1923 (Box 116)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 116)
  - Indiana Properties (South Bend, Goshen, New Carlisle)
    - Papers, 1916-1921 (Box 116)
    - Papers, 1922-1924 (Box 116)
    - Papers, 1925-1928 (Box 116)
  - Duck Island (Gift to the University of Michigan), Papers, 1929-1932 (Box 116)
  - Perry Tract (Gift to Purdue University)
    - Papers, 1929-1930; 1938 (Box 116)
    - Correspondence, 1907-1913; 1923; 2 folders (Box 116)
    - Land descriptions (Box 116)
    - Abstracts, 1905-1907; 1923 (Box 116)
    - Contracts, 1901; 1907-1913; 1923 (Box 116)
  - Turtle Dove Plantation (Georgia), Papers, 1929-1930; 2 folders (Box 116)
  - Texas Farms (Grayson and Bell Counties)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 116)
    - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 116)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box 116)
  - Upper Peninsula Lands (Purdue University), 1929-1930 (Box 116)
  - Goodbear Farm
    - Correspondence, 1917-1927; 2 folders (Box 116)
    - Abstracts, deeds, contracts, 1917 (Box 116)
    - Financial reports, 1917-1925 (Box 116)
  - South Bend-St. Joseph County Properties
    - Correspondence, 1907-1921; 6 folders (Box 116)
    - Financial records, 1904-1920 (Box 116)
  - Margaret A. Osborn Estate
    - Correspondence, 1913-1918; 4 folders (Box 116)
    - Legal papers, 1914-1917 (Box 116)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 116)
  - Affairs of Eugene B. Osborn
    - Correspondence, 1912-1917; 1921-1931; 2 folders (Box 117)
    - Legal papers, 1912-1917 (Box 117)
  - Affairs of W.D. Osborn
    - Correspondence, 1908-1920; 4 folders (Box 117)
  - Osborn House, South Bend, Indiana, 1912 (Box 117)
  - Stephen P. Osborn Farm papers, 1914-1916 (Box 117)
  - Land transactions files
    - Waldo Avery files, 1904-1905; 2 folders (Box 117)
    - Ezra Richardson estate, 1904-1905 (Box 117)
    - Various, 1886-1903 (Box 152)
    - Various, 1899-1904; 3 folders (Box 117)
    - Various, 1902-1903 (Box 117)
    - Various, 1904-1906 (Box 152)
    - Various, 1905-1907; 2 folders (Box 152)
    - Various, 1908-1909 (Box 152)
    - Various, 1910-1919 (Box 152)
    - Various, 1912-1916 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1914; 2 folders (Box 118)
    - Various, 1914-1917 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1915-1916 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1915-1918 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1916 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1917-1918 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1917-1920 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1918-1920 (Box 118)
    - Various, 1920-1928 (Box 152)
    - Timber Warden reports, 1908-1909 (Box 117)
    - Property lists of CSO, 1 volume (Box 117)
    - Timber reports, circa 1908-1911; 8 folders (Box 117)
    - Timber reports, 1912-1919; 5 folders (Box 118)
      (no 1918)
    - Worth County, Georgia, 1885-1911 (Box 152)
  - Timber: Sage Tract (Box 118)
  - Timber: McIntosh Tract papers, 1905 (Box 118)
  - Timber: Berry Lands papers, 1905 (Box 118)
  - Miscellaneous timber and land descriptions, 1904-1905 (Box 118)
  - Miscellaneous timber maps and estimates, 2 folders (Box 118)
  - Timber estimates, 1920 (Box 118)
  - Duck Is, 1920-1922 (Box 119)
  - 1920, 3 folders (Box 119)
  - 1920-1921 (Box 119)
    (Detroit, Mackinac & Marquette Land Company)
  - 1921, 2 folders (Box 119)
  - Espanore Farm, 1913-1916; 6 folders (Box 119)
  - Espanore Farm, Lansing, Michigan, breeders of Holstein-Friesian cattle
    (CSO was co-owner with Adam E. Ferguson)
    - Correspondence, 1911-1926; 10 folders (Box 119)
    - Legal papers, 1893-1926; 4 folders (Box 119)
    - Financial reports, 1916-1922 (Box 119)
    - Maps (Box 119)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 119)
  - Ferguson Motor Company ledger, 1 volume (Box 119)
  - Ferguson Motor Company cash book, 1922-1924 (Volume 1)
  - circa 1920-1930, 0.67 linear feet (Box 120)
    (Unprocessed)
  - Financial papers
    - General, 1926-1927 (Box 120)
    - Income tax correspondence and statements, 1924; 1926-1932; 6 folders (Box 120)
    - Ojibway Park Hotel Company, 1936-1940 (Box 120)
    - Account book, 1906-1940 (Box 120)
    - Receipts and disbursements, 1896-1915; 8 folders (Box 120)
- Topical Files, 1912-1944
  Topical Files (1912-1944; 1 linear foot) is an artificially created series of foldered material on different subjects. Of most significance are the numerous files detailing Osborn's lobbying efforts in the 1930s proposing the building of a bridge to span the straits of Mackinac.
  - Africa trip, 1913; 2 folders (Box 121)
  - Bay City convention of 1912 letter about, 1940 (Box 121)
  - Calorie Dollar, 1919 (Box 121)
  - Census-CSO research into area of the state of Michigan to be used in the 1940 census, 1939-1941, 3 folders (Box 121)
  - Chase Osborn Day
    - 1939, 2 folders (Box 121)
    - 1940 (Box 121)
    - 1971 (Box 121)
  - Court packing plan, 1937
    - Correspondence (Box 121)
    - Newsclippings (Box 121)
  - Dogs (sales and breeding material) (Box 121)
    (sample)
  - Flood control, 1935-1937 (Box 121)
  - Indian land mining and timber regulations, 1916 (Box 121)
  - Iron Ore
    - General, 1916-1923 (Box 121)
    - African Ore proposition, 1923 (Box 121)
  - Jefferson Davis Memorial Park, 1935 (Box 121)
  - Mackinac Bridge (proposed straits of Mackinac Bridge), 1935-1941
    - Correspondence A-Z, 1935-1936; 5 folders (Box 121)
    - Correspondence, 1936-1940 (Box 121)
    - General, 1936 (Box 121)
      (history, speeches, etc.)
    - Clippings, 1936; 3 folders (Box 121)
    - Clippings, 1937-1941 (Box 121)
  - Masonic Lodge (Florence, Wisconsin) (Box 121)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 121)
  - Poems and songs, 2 folders (Box 121)
    (not by CSO)
  - Programs-souvenir (Box 121)
  - Prohibition (Box 121)
  - Purdue Club (Box 121)
  - Railroads, nationalization of, December 1937-February 1938 (Box 121)
  - Richard (Father Gabriel Richard Society), 1936-1939 (Box 122)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, analysis of his speaking style by Chase S. Osborn (Box 122)
  - St. Lawrence Seaway Project, 1940-1944 (Box 122)
  - Sault Ste. Marie Art Gallery papers, 1913-1919 (Box 122)
  - Sigma Chi fraternity (copies of publication with material about CSO) (Box 122)
  - Soo Curling Club (Box 122)
- Writings, 1900-1948
  Writings (1900-1948; 3 linear feet) includes copies of newspaper columns written by Osborn for the newspaper, files pertaining to the publication of his various books, and other writings.
  - Articles for newspapers, etc
    - Undated (Box 122)
    - 1900-1917 (Box 122)
    - 1930s undated (Box 122)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 122)
    - 1940s undated, 7 folders (Box 122)
    - 1940 (Box 122)
    - 1941 (Box 122)
    - 1942, 5 folders (Box 122)
    - 1943, 3 folders (Box 122)
    - 1944, 3 folders (Box 122)
    - 1945, 2 folders (Box 122)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 122)
  - Book files
    (include clippings, correspondence with publisher, etc.)
    - The Andean Land (1909) (Box 123)
      (Illustrations used in book, scrapbook)
    - The Iron Hunter (1919), 1916-1925 (Box 123)
      (Correspondence, reviews, clippings, scrapbooks, etc.)
    - Madagascar (1924) (Box 123)
      (Correspondence, reviews, clippings, etc.)
    - Conquest of a Continent, 1939-1941 (Box 123)
      (Correspondence and scrapbook)
    - Schoolcraft-Longfellow-Hiawatha (1942)
      - Research correspondence, 1940-1942; 4 folders (Box 123)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 123)
      - Clippings and reviews (Box 123)
    - Schoolcraft-Longfellow-Hiawatha (1942)
      - Post-publication correspondence, 1943; 4 folders (Box 124)
    - An Accolade for Chase S. Osborn: Home, State, and National Tributes on the Occasion of Chase S. Osborn Day October 4, 1939, 1940 (Box 151)
    - The Andean Land, 1909 (Box 151)
      (by Chase S. Osborn)
    - Chase Salmon Osborn (Box 151)
      (by Robert M. Warner)
    - Eighty and On, 1941 (Box 151)
      (by Stella Osborn)
    - The Iron Hunter, 1922 (Box 151)
    - Jusmine Springs, 1953 (Box 151)
    - A Tale of Possum Poke in Possum Lane, 1946 (Box 151)
    - You Come Too, 1961 (Box 151)
      (by Thomas W, Nason)
  - Other writings
    - Firefly's Light miscellanea (book written by Emerson Hough and distributed by CSO), 1916-1919 (Box 124)
    - Michigan article written for National Geographic Magazine, 1923-1924, 4 folders (Box 124)
    - "Miscellaneous writings", volume I (Box 124)
      (clippings from various publications)
    - "Miscellaneous writings", volume II (Box 124)
    - Articles written from Detroit Sunday Times entitled "Michigan: Romance of a State", 1924-1925 (Box 124)
    - Joint projects with Stella Osborn (include reviews of books) (Box 124)
    - An Accolade for Chase S. Osborn, correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 124)
    - Eighty and On (Stella Osborn), correspondence, December 1940-1941; 2 folders (Box 124)
    - Book reviews by CSO (Box 124)
    - Manuscripts of various writings, 6 folders (Box 124)
    - Publications containing articles by CSO (Box 124)
- Scrapbooks, 1883-1949
  The Scrapbooks (ca. 1883-1949; 18.5 linear feet) series includes a set of personal scrapbooks maintained by Osborn from the mid-1890s to 1941 with loose clippings that continue up to his death in 1949. There are also miscellaneous scrapbooks covering specific activities in Osborn's life such as his candidacy for Congress in 1896, his gubernatorial campaign in 1910, and his trip to Africa in 1913.
  - Personal Scrapbooks, 1898-1932; 123 volumes
    - 1898-1900 (Box 125)
      (no. 1-7)
    - 1900-1908 (Box 126)
      (no. 8-18)
    - 1908-1909 (Box 127)
      (no. 19-28b)
    - 1908-1910 (Box 128)
      (no. 29-37)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 129)
      (no. 38-48)
    - 1911 (Box 130)
      (no. 49-59)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 131)
      (no. 60-70)
    - 1912 (Box 132)
      (no. 71-80)
    - 1913-1915 (Box 133)
      (no. 81-91)
    - 1915-1918 (Box 134)
      (no. 91-102)
    - 1918-1925 (Box 135)
      (no. 103-113)
    - 1925-1932 (Box 136)
      (no. 114-123)
  - Florence, Wisconsin, circa 1883-1884; 2 volumes (Box 137)
  - Personal, 1890-1894 (Box 137)
  - State Game Warden candidacy, 1894 (Box 137)
  - Game Warden Scrapbooks, 1895-1899; 5 volumes (Box 137)
  - Candidate for Congress, 1896; 2 volumes (Box 137)
    (see also oversize pages from scrapbook in box 145)
  - Personal, 1896-1898 (Box 137)
  - Political, 1895-1896 (Box 138)
  - Free Silver Scrapbook (Box 138)
  - Currency Scrapbook, 1899 (Box 138)
  - Railroad Commissioner Scrapbooks, 1899-1902; 5 volumes (Box 138)
  - Personal Scrapbook, 1900-1902 (Box 139)
  - Personal, 1902-1903 (Box 139)
  - Timber and Iron Scrapbook, 1904-1908 (Box 139)
  - Scrapbook from the campaign, 1910 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1909-1914 (Volume 3)
  - Political, 1912 (Box 139)
  - African Trip Scrapbook, 1913-1914 (Box 139)
  - Personal Scrapbooks, 1898-1948; 3 volumes
    - 1933-1934, 3 volumes (Box 139)
    - 1934-1937, 7 volumes (Box 140)
    - 1937-1942, 8 volumes (Box 141)
    - 1944-1948 (Box 142)
    - 1894-1900 (Box 142)
    - Personal, 1909-1934 (Box 142)
      (very scattered)
  - Scrapbooks containing Sault Ste. Marie Evening News column, 1940-1945; 3 volumes (Box 142)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 143)
- Photographs, 1870-1949
  Photographs (ca. 1870-ca. 1949; 1.2 linear feet) includes formal and informal portraits of Osborn and other members of the Osborn family; photographs of Osborn at work and at his homes on Duck Island, Michigan and in Georgia. There are also collected photos relating to Upper Peninsula life and activities, and to Osborn's various activities, particularly hunting.
  - Family photograph Album (Box 143)
  - Formal Portraits
    - Photographs (Box 144)
    - Photographs of painting and sculpture (Box 144)
    - Half-tones cartoons, drawings and prints (Box 144)
      (see also oversize box 145)
    - Youth and early career (Box 144)
    - Middle years, circa 1890-1910 (Box 144)
      (as governor and public figure and hunting and camping scenes)
    - Later years (Box 144)
  - Informal photographs
    - As governor, campaigning, etc (Box 144)
    - As regent of the University of Michigan (Box 144)
    - Later years
      - General (Box 144)
      - Duck Island (Box 144)
      - Poulan, Georgia, 2 folders (Box 144)
    - With Stella Osborn (Box 144)
    - With dignitaries; receiving awards (Box 144)
    - With family members (Box 144)
    - Last year and in hospital, 1949 (Box 144)
    - Funeral, 1949 (Box 144)
  - Subject files (not always including CSO)
    - Banquets: 42nd Grand Chapter Banquet Sigma Chi Fraternity September 5, 1935 and 20th Annual Banquet of the Marquette Club of Chicago, February 12, 1908, 1908-1935 (Folder 1)
    - Bay City Convention (locked armory), 1912 (Box 144)
    - Dearfoot Hunting Lodge, 1905-1910; 2 folders (Box 144)
    - Duck Island and other Upper Peninsula views, circa 1940s (Box 144)
    - Friends and colleagues (Box 144)
    - Lake Superior (Isle Royale, Pigeon Falls) (Box 144)
    - Miscellaneous (Michigan Infantry, 8th Regiment), circa 1910 (Box 144)
    - Newberry (views, train siding and stone figures) (Box 144)
    - Petoskey Portland Cement Company, 1920 (Box 144)
    - Pictured Rocks, Michigan (Box 144)
    - Ramsay, Michigan (Bridge, Mine) (Box 144)
    - Rangoon trip (Box 144)
    - Rockland, Michigan (high school) (Box 144)
    - Sault Ste. Marie (views, monuments, house) (Box 144)
    - Smith farm (Goshen, Indiana) (Box 144)
    - Taft (Pres.) visit to Sault Ste. Marie, 1911 (Box 144)
    - Tahquamenon River, Michigan (Box 144)
    - Wisconsin (Florence), Masons (Box 144)
  - Family (identified), 5 folders (Box 144)
  - Family (David and William H. Reed); drawings (Box 144)
  - Family Album contents, 2 folders (Box 144)
  - Family (Sarah Osborn; Almira Goldthwaite): daguerreotypes (Box 144)
  - Citations, clippings, etc (Box 145)
  - Photographs (Box 145)
  - Cartoons, drawings, etc (Box 145)
  - Campaign posters (Box 145)